Birth Control Collection, 1923-2000
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Birth control collection
1923-2000
MS 451
1 box; 27 volumes (3.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
This small collection is comprised of mostly books, plus some pamphlets, flyers, and other. Documents uses and misuses of contraception; family planning; sex in marriage; sex instruction; histories of the treatment of contraception by the church; population problems; fertility; and sterility.
This small collection is comprised of mostly books, plus one box of pamphlets, flyers, and other publications dating from 1923 to 2000, with the bulk of the materials dating from the 1930s. Topics relate primarily to uses and misuses of contraception; family planning; sex in marriage; sex instruction; histories of the treatment of contraception by the church; population problems; fertility; and sterility.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions to collection are expected.
History of the Collection
Most of the books in this collection were transferred from Neilson Library, Smith College. Other materials were either purchased or given to the Sophia Smith Collection by various donors.
Search Terms
Birth control--History--20th century--Sources; Contraceptives--Research--History; Human reproduction--Political aspects; Population policy--History--20th century; Sex in marriage; Sex instruction--United States--History; Hygiene, Sexual--History--20th century; Women's health services--United States--History--20th century; Women--Health and hygiene
- General
  - Publications and fliers, 1950-2002, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Birth control methods (handwritten and unidentified), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Lanteen Brown diaphram box (Box 1, Folder 2b)
- Books on Shelf
  - A Thousand Marriages: A Medical Study of Sex Adjustment, by Robert Latou Dickinson and Lura Beam, 1931 [foreword by Havelock Ellis]
  - And the Poor Get Children, by Lee Rainwater and Karol Kane Weinstein, 1960
  - Biological and Medical Aspects of Contraception: Papers and Discussions Presented at the American Conference on Birth Control and National Recovery, edited by Margaret Sanger, 1934
  - Birth Control and the State: A Plea and Forecast, by C.P. Blacker, 1926
  - Birth Control: Its Use and Misuse, by Dorothy Dunbar Bromley, 1934 [introduction by R. L. Dickinson]
  - Birth Control Today: A Practical Approach to Intelligent Family Planning, by Leon F. Whitley, 1960
  - Birth Control in Practice: Analysis of Ten Thousand Case Histories of the Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau, by Marie F. Kopp, 1933
  - Birth Control on Trial, by Lella Secor Florence, 1930 [foreword by Sir Humphrey Rolleston, Bart.; introductory note by F.H.A. Marshall]
  - Contraception: A History of its Treatment by the Catholic Theologians and Canonists, by John T. Noonan, Jr., 1965
  - Controlled Fertility: An Evaluation of Clinic Services, by Regine K. Stix and Frank W. Notestein, 1940
  - Family Planning Movement in Japan, published by The Population Problems Research Council, 1953 [contents include speech by Margaret Sanger, essay by Shoichi Arai
  - Family Limitation, by John Ryan, 1956 [foreword by Alan Keenan]
  - Fertility and Sterility in Marriage: Their Voluntary Promotion and Limitation, by Th. H. Van De Velde; translated by F. W. Stella Browne, 1934
  - The Fifth International Conference on Planned Parenthood: Report of the Proceedings [Theme: Overpopulation and Family Planning], published by International Planned Parenthood Federation, 1955
  - Fruits of Philosophy or the Private Consumption of Adult People, by Charles Knowlton, 1937 [edited by Norman Hines]
  - Medical History of Contraception, by Norman Himes, 1936 [foreword by R.L. Dickinson]
  - The Modern Method of Birth Control, by Thurston S. Welton, 1935
  - Population and Planned Parenthood in India, by S. Chandrasekhar, 1955 [introduction by Julian Huxley]
  - The Power of the Pill: Oral Contraceptives and Women's Career and Marriage Decisions, by Claudia Golden and Laurence F. Katz, 2000
  - The Practice of Contraception, edited by Margaret Sanger and Hannah M. Stone, 1931 [foreword by R.L. Dickinson}
  - Report on the Sex Question by the Swedish Population Commission, translated and edited by Virginia Clay Hamilton, 1940
  - Seed: A Novel of Birth Control, by Charles G. Norris, 1940
  - Sex Problem in India, by N.S. Phadke, 1927 [foreword by Margaret Sanger]
  - The Single Woman: A Medical Study in Sex Education, by R. L. Dickinson and Lura Beam, 1934
  - The Third International Conference on Planned Parenthood: Report of the Proceedings, published by The Family Planning Association, 1952
  - Tomorrow's Children: Proceedings of the Southern Conference on Tomorrow's Children (held in Atlanta, GA, November 9-11, 1939), published by the Birth Control Federation of America, 1939
  - The Truth About the New Birth Control Pills, by John Devaney and Philip Reaves, 1961
  - Wise Parenthood: The Treatise on Birth Control for Married People, A Practical Sequel to "Married Love": eleventh edition, by Marie Carmichael Stopes, 1923 [introduction by Arnold Bennett]